Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre fonds
1974 - 1996
F-76
Q101536641
88 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre
The Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre Society was established as the result of efforts by a small group of women who met originally as a consciousness-raising group in 1974. They saw the need to establish a place for women to meet, give support, share their knowledge and experience, and to have a place that could provide a safe environment for women in crisis. With the support of the city councils of Coquitlam, Port Coquitlam, and Port Moody, the women were given an old concession stand to convert into the Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre in 1975. The society itself incorporated under the British Columbia Societies Act in 1975, and ran the centre, which provides not only a meeting place, but also information, referrals and volunteer opportunities. The society also lobbies government, and is involved in community projects, such as the Coquitlam Women's Transition House.
The Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre is run as a collective. Committees are formed as required. Each committee is responsible to the membership and gives a report at the general monthly meetings. A steering committee coordinates all activities. It consists of five women with a rotating membership; every three months one of its members is replaced in order to allow more women in the centre to be involved in the process of decision making. This structure ensures that there are experienced members on the steering committee at all times, but allows new (and inexperienced) members to participate and learn. The steering committee also ensures that decisions made at general meetings are carried out and brings issues forward to the general membership for action.
The Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre continues to be active to this day, and operates under the guiding principles of feminism, including the idea that women have the right to be full and equal members of society. It is a member of the National Action Committee for the Status of Women; the BC/Yukon Association of Women's Centres; the Legal, Education, and Action Fund; and the BC Coalition for Abortion Clinics.
published
Full
Revised
Title is based on the provenance of the fonds.
The fonds consists of records created, received and collected by the Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre in carrying out their objectives. Records reflect the administration and organization of the centre; financial arrangements and funding; projects, programs and activities the centre is involved with; its relationship with other feminist organizations; and publications. Includes constitution, by-laws, minutes of general meetings, minutes of steering committee meetings, membership lists, reports, financial records, correspondence, and publications.
Original order was maintained by the Archivist where possible. Where no order was apparent, the materials were arranged by the Archivist.
Community life; Women
The collection was donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by the Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals are expected.
Please consult the inventory for the Women's Bookstore Collection, F-111.
Some files may contain personal information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Series descriptions and file lists are available.
- Administration and organization records, 1975 - 1984; F-76-1; 22 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the administration and organization of the Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre. Records reflect the establishment of the centre, its functions and activities, and its internal organization. Also reflects the structural relationship of committees, and members. Includes the constitution, by-laws, minutes from general meetings and from the steering committee, records of other centre committees, membership lists, policies and procedures, annual reports, and centre statistics.
  - Constitution and By-Laws - Societies Act, 1975; F-76-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - General meetings - minutes, 1975; F-76-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - General meetings - minutes, 1976; F-76-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - General meetings - minutes, 1977 - 1978; F-76-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - General meetings - minutes, 1979 - 1980; F-76-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - General meetings - minutes, 1981 - 1982; F-76-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - General meetings - minutes, 1983; F-76-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - Steering Committee - minutes, 1975; F-76-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
    Pending review
  - Steering Committee - minutes, 1976 - 1979; F-76-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - Education Committee, 1976 - 1979; F-76-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - Letter Lobby Committee, 1976 - 1977; F-76-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - Letter Lobby Committee, 1979 - 1981; F-76-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - Library Committee, 1975 - 1979; F-76-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - Newsletter Committee, 1975 - 1977; F-76-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - Special Projects Committee - Child Care Centre (Paddington Station), 1978 - 1979; F-76-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - Membership Lists, 1975 - 1984; F-76-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - Policies and Procedures, 1975; F-76-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 76-1)
  - Policies and Procedures Manual, 1983; F-76-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
  - Annual Reports, 1976 - 1979; F-76-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
  - Annual Reports, 1977; F-76-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
  - Annual Reports, 1980 - 1982; F-76-1-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
  - Annual Reports, 1983; F-76-1-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
  - Annual Reports, 1984; F-76-1-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
  - Centre Statistics, 1975; F-76-1-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
  - Centre Statistics, 1976; F-76-1-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
  - Centre Statistics, 1982 - 1983; F-76-1-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
- Financial records, 1975 - 1984; F-76-2; 11 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the finances of the Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre. Records reflect treasurer's reports, grant applications, and funding arrangements with the Provincial government and the United Way. Includes reports, budgets, monthly income statements, and correspondence.
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1977 - 1983; F-76-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
  - Funding, 1975 - 1979; F-76-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 76-2)
  - Ministry of Human Resources - agreements / grant and funding applications, 1975 - 1984; F-76-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 76-3)
  - United Way - funding and correspondence, 1979; F-76-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 76-3)
  - United Way - funding and correspondence, 1980; F-76-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 76-3)
  - United Way - funding and correspondence, 1981; F-76-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 76-3)
  - United Way - funding and correspondence, 1982; F-76-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 76-3)
  - United Way - funding and correspondence, 1983; F-76-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 76-3)
- Correspondence, 1974 - 1987; F-76-3; 13 cm of textual records
  Series consists of correspondence created and received by the Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre in carrying out their objectives. Records reflect general correspondence relating to centre programs, requests for information, association with other feminist groups, and the like. Also includes correspondence files relating to specific issues and topics such as Wages for Housework, the National Film Board, and letters of support for the centre.
  - Correspondence, 1974 - 1975; F-76-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 76-3)
  - Correspondence, 1975 - 1987; F-76-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 76-3)
  - Correspondence, 1976; F-76-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 76-3)
  - Correspondence, 1977; F-76-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Correspondence, 1978 - 1979; F-76-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Correspondence, 1981 - 1982; F-76-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Correspondence, 1983; F-76-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Correspondence, 1984; F-76-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Correspondence - Doug Collins incident, 1983; F-76-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Correspondence - Judy Erola, 1983; F-76-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Correspondence - Letters of Support, 1975 - 1979; F-76-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Correspondence - Men's Support Group, 1983; F-76-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Correspondence - National Film Board, 1979; F-76-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Correspondence - Wages for Housework, 1976; F-76-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
- Projects, programs and activities, 1975 - 1984; F-76-4; 15 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to projects, programs, and activities of the Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre. Records reflect letter writing campaigns, and special projects such as the Douglas College Cut protest, the Coquitlam Transition House, and the Pat Isert Memorial fund. Also reflects the centre's involvement with specific issues such as discrimination in local sports and Red Hot Video. Includes correspondence, press releases, minutes, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, hand bills, and financial records.
  - Community Telidon Network, 1983; F-76-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Discrimination - girls' hockey, 1981; F-76-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Doctors' Directory, 1979; F-76-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Douglas College Cut Protest - correspondence / support letters, 1982; F-76-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 76-4)
  - Douglas College Cut Protest - general 1/2, 1982; F-76-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
  - Douglas College Cut Protest - general 2/2, 1982; F-76-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
  - Douglas College Cut Protest - information, 1982; F-76-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
  - High School Women's Studies Program, 1977; F-76-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
  - International Women's Day / Year, 1975; F-76-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
  - Pat Isert Memorial Fund, 1979; F-76-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
  - Pornography, 1982 - 1983; F-76-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
  - Pornography subject file: Red Hot Video chain store campaign, 1982; F-76-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
    File contains records made or received by the Women's Centre in participating in a public protest campaign against violent pornography retailed at Red Hot Video in its various outlet stores in the Lower Mainland. Records include correspondence, press releases, newspaper clippings, and brochures and pamphlets.
    Open, no restrictions
    Access review (Jun 16, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
  - Rally for Action newsletter, 1976; F-76-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
  - Transition House - Coquitlam, 1977 - 1978; F-76-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
  - Transition House - Coquitlam, 1980 - 1981; F-76-4-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
  - Women's Centre Conference, 1984; F-76-4-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 76-5)
- Liaison with associated groups, 1975 - 1984; F-76-5; 12 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre's association with other women's groups. Records reflect liaison with the Vancouver Status of Women, the BC Federation of Women, women's centres throughout the Province, and others. Includes correspondence, reports, membership lists, agenda, minutes, newsletters, and ephemera.
  - Vancouver Status of Women, 1975 - 1979; F-76-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - United Way - Human Care Needs Study, 1979; F-76-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - Voluntary Information Services Exchange, 1975 - 1977; F-76-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - Women's Centres, 1975 - 1976; F-76-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - B.C. Federation of Women, 1975 - 1976; F-76-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - B.C. Federation of Women, 1977 - 1979; F-76-5-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - Fraser Valley Women's Coalition - minutes and papers, 1976 - 1977; F-76-5-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - Fraser Valley Women's Coalition - newsletter, 1977; F-76-5-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - Status of Women - papers, 1979 - 1981; F-76-5-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - B.C./Yukon Women's Advocate Committee, 1975; F-76-5-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - Coquitlam groups, 1975 - 1980; F-76-5-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
  - Women's groups, 1979 - 1984; F-76-5-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 76-6)
- Publications, 1975 - 1996; F-76-6; 13 cm of textual records
  Series consists of publications produced and collected by the Port Coquitlam Area Women's Centre. Includes the centre newsletter Women Today, a history of women's centres, guides, bulletins, newsletters from other organizations and newspaper clippings.
  - Story of a Women's Centre, 1979; F-76-6-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1975; F-76-6-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1976; F-76-6-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1977; F-76-6-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1978; F-76-6-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1979; F-76-6-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1980; F-76-6-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1981; F-76-6-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1982; F-76-6-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1983; F-76-6-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1984; F-76-6-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newsletter - Women Today, 1992 - 1996; F-76-6-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Guide to the B.C. Women's Movement, 1975; F-76-6-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Ishtar, 1975 - 1976; F-76-6-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Priorities, 1980 - 1987; F-76-6-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Resource Bulletin, 1980; F-76-6-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Transition Houses for Women, 1978; F-76-6-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - WICCA, 1975; F-76-6-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 76-7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1975 - 1982; F-76-6-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 76-7)